{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This country was saved by the arrival of Anton von L’Estocq’s forces during a battle in which 11,000 enemy cavalry charged through a heavy snowstorm. This country’s troops crossed the Alle River in an attempt to defeat Jean Lannes before aid arrived; however, that assault backfired on the Count of Bennigsen, and this country was forced to sign the Treaty of Tilsit. The loser at the Battles of Eylau and Friedland was, for ten points, what country whose refusal to follow the Continental System prompted a French invasion in 1812?",
      "answer": "Russian Empire"
    },
    {
      "question": "This state’s Camp Jackson riot and subsequent massacre was triggered by Nathaniel Lyon’s arrest of the state militia. That massacre led to the brief Price-Harney Truce between the federal government and this state’s government, which ultimately collapsed at the Battle of Wilson’s Creek near Springfield. Many people from this state fought as guerrilla bushwhackers, often against Jayhawkers in a neighboring state. For ten points, name this state in the Civil War whose “Border Ruffians” rushed in to fight in “Bleeding Kansas.”",
      "answer": "Missouri"
    },
    {
      "question": "A thinker from this philosophical movement thought that “What’s a mistake but a kind of take?” was one of the secrets of the universe after inhaling too much nitrous oxide. The author of Making It Explicit, Robert Brandom, is considered a revivalist of this philosophical school with his teacher, Richard Rorty. A book titled for this philosophical school is subtitled “A New Name for Some Old Ways of Thinking.” For ten points, name this American philosophical movement that included C.S. Peirce [PURSE], John Dewey, and William James.",
      "answer": "pragmatism"
    },
    {
      "question": "This dynasty fled south after a war where Fire Lances used at the Battle of De’an. This dynasty used Tiger Cave Kilns to create Guan Ware instead of Ru Ware ceramics. Following the short-lived Qingli reforms, this dynasty introduced the New Policies under reformer Wang Anshi, who was opposed by Sima Guang. After defeating the Liao, the Jurchen Jin Dynasty invaded this dynasty forcing it to move its capital from Kaifeng to Hangzhou. For ten points, name this Chinese dynasty that fell after the invasion of the Yuan under Kublai Khan.",
      "answer": "Song Dynasty"
    },
    {
      "question": "A very early example of this art form, Seelewig, was produced in Nuremberg in 1644. The earliest examples of this form include Jacopo Peri’s Dafne and the oldest one still performed, The Coronation of Poppea by Claudio Monteverdi. Rival types of this art form in the 18th century included seria and buffa; examples of the latter include The Barber of Seville. A librettist writes the words for, for ten points, what art form that combines theatrical staging and, usually, classical music?",
      "answer": "opera"
    },
    {
      "question": "Following his 1978 death, this man’s wife Muriel took over his Senate seat. At a 1948 national convention, this man stated that “The time has arrived for the Democratic Party to [...] walk forth- rightfully into the bright sunshine of human rights.” This man succeeded Eugene McCarthy as senator from Minnesota after being nominated for President at a convention where riots broke out in Chicago. For ten points, name this Democratic politician who lost the 1968 election to Richard Nixon.",
      "answer": "Hubert Horatio Humphrey, Jr."
    },
    {
      "question": "One of this religion’s scriptures is called the Holy Piby. This religion celebrates a 1966 plane landing at Palisadoes Airport with its Grounation Day holiday. This religion is divided into denominations like Nyahbinghi called “Mansions” and keeps a diet caled Ital [EYE-tall]. For ten points, name this religion which regards Haile Selassie as the second coming of Christ, a Jamaican movement famous for its practitioners’ dreadlocks and cannabis use.",
      "answer": [
        "Rastafarianism",
        "word forms, including Rastafari"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A Bible used in this event is maintained by St. John’s Lodge. The central figure of this event arrived by barge to Murray’s Wharf and, after it, was forced to walk to his residence at Franklin House since too many people were crowding the streets. Robert Livingston administered an oath to the subject of this event, who allegedly added the words “so help me God” at the end. This event included a speech given outside of Federal Hall in New York City. For ten points, name this April 30, 1789 event that marked the start of the first Presidency.",
      "answer": "inauguration of George Washington"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man agreed to a truce with England in the Treaty of Picquigny, allowing him to focus his forces against the League of the Public Weal. This man revolted against his father in the failed Praguerie and subsequently fled to Philip the Good’s court. After his greatest foe was slain at Nancy, this ruler annexed Picardy. The death of Charles the Bold allowed this man to take control of Burgundy. For ten points, name this French monarch whose diplomatic cunning earned him his nickname.",
      "answer": [
        "Louis XI",
        "Louis the Prudent",
        "Louis the Universal Spider"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A politician from this state briefly ran for President in 2015 and condemned “immigration without assimilation” as “invasion.” Another politician from this state lost his 2015 bid for governor after a scandal involving him soliciting prostitutes; that man was David Vitter, who lost to a man who is now the only Democratic governor in the Deep South. For ten points, name this state that has been governed by John Bel Edwards, Bobby Jindal, and Kathleen Blanco, who served during Hurricane Katrina.",
      "answer": "Louisiana"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Jean Delay diagnosed one of the central figures of these events with hysterical amnesia. Former Hungarian ambassador John Montgomery helped Miklos Horthy avoid being targeted by these events. Geoffrey Lawrence and Francis Biddle were presiding figures at this event, where Robert Jackson gave an opening speech. Hjalmar Schacht was acquitted of conspiring and planning crimes against peace at this event. Rudolf Hess was among the men transported to Spandau Prison after, for ten points, what post-war trials against Nazi officials?",
        "answer": "Nuremberg Trials"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man, one of the 24 defendants at Nuremberg, was tried in absentia because his rumored death during the fall of Berlin could not be confirmed. This man’s remains were eventually found in 1972.",
        "answer": "Martin Bormann"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "ThismandiedinhissleepathissummerhomeinFlorida,TheCasements.InadepictionbyPuck,this man’s company was shown as an octopus grabbing lawmakers and reaching for the White House. Despite his son having ordered the action, this man was criticized for the deadly force brought against protesting coal miners at his Ludlow mine. This man’s corrupt business practices were exposed by muckraker Ida Tarbell, who wrote a history of his company. For ten points, name this richest ever American, the founder of Standard Oil.",
        "answer": "John D. Rockefeller"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ida Tarbell’s expose of Rockefeller’s practices was published by this magazine, which was edited by Lincoln Steffens.",
        "answer": "McClure’s Magazine"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A ruler of this empire ordered Ketevan the Martyr’s execution after she refused to renounce Christianity. Although the Shirley brothers helped modernize this empire’s army, its troops suffered a defeat against the Hotaki Empire at the Battle of Gulnabad. They’re not Bulgars, but after this dynasty won the Battle of Merv, its first ruler had his enemy’s skull fashioned into a drinking goblet. That man’s son, Tahmasp I, signed the Peace of Amasya with a rival empire that won the Battle of Chaldiran under the leadership of Selim the Grim. Ismail I founded, for ten points, what Iranian dynasty that practiced Shia Islam?",
        "answer": "Safavid Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Safavid shah, who diminished the power of the Qizilbash, moved the Safavid capital to Isfahan. He allied with the English East India Company to retake Hormuz from the Portuguese.",
        "answer": "Abbas I or Abbas the Great"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A travelogue named for the scent of females from this place was written by a man whose ceramic of a female savage inspired a figure in Pablo Picasso’s Young Ladies of Avignon. A work depicting people from this place should be viewed from right to left and was finished after its painter attempted suicide by overdosing on arsenic. In that piece about this place, each of the major groups acts alongside a blue Buddha-like idol that is meant to represent “the Beyond.” The work Where Do We Come From? What Are We? Where Are We Going? was set on, for ten points, what French Polynesian island that was frequented by Paul Gauguin?",
        "answer": "Tahiti"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Due to its shared setting and subjects, Gauguin’s painting The Spirit of the Dead Watching was compared to this painting, which caused an uproar at the 1865 Paris Salon. Despite her oppositional gaze, the maid is ignored by the title figure of this work.",
        "answer": "Olympia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler allegedly threw a group of fettered Jews into the Dead Sea to test its buoyancy after destroying Jericho. This ruler seized power by joining forces with the Syrian governor Mucianus, who encouraged this man to implement his toilet tax. This man met Josephus, whom he would later patronize, while putting down the first Jewish rebellion in AD 66. For ten points, name this first Flavian emperor who ended the Year of the Four Emperors.",
        "answer": "Vespasian"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Shortly before his death, Vespasian sent this general to govern Britannia and conquer Wales, which he summarily did. This man’s deeds were recorded by Tacitus, his son-in-law.",
        "answer": "Gnaeus Julius Agricola"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This company was criticized for deciding not to remove footage of the Lac-M´egantic disaster, one of the deadliest train derailments in Canadian history, as stock footage in one of its 2018 films. A company called “Qwikster” was to be spunoff from this company in 2011, but CEO Reed Hastings quickly changed course. Programs like Narcos and the American version of House of Cards were produced by, for ten points, what streaming service that released Bird Box in 2018?",
        "answer": "Netflix"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Narcos was a three-season drama set in Colombia about this drug kingpin, who was killed in 1993.",
        "answer": "Pablo Escobar"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This policy was formulated in a memorandum authored by William Woodville Rockhill. The Nine-Power Treaty upheld this policy, which was issued as part of U.S. foreign policy in a namesake 1899 note. Elihu Root continued this policy, which was first implemented under his predecessor as Secretary of State. This policy was nearly abandoned after the Boxer Rebellion, which threatened to break this policy’s central nation into spheres of influences. For ten points, name this American policy aimed at keeping China’s economy accessible to all major powers.",
        "answer": "Open Door Policy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Secretary of State issued the original Open Door Note while serving under President McKinley. This man, who worked as a secretary for Abraham Lincoln, negotiated a failed treaty with Tom´as Herr´an of Colombia in 1903.",
        "answer": "John Hay"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Defenders of this city repurposed naval guns from the Aurora to defend Pulkovo Heights. After its deployment in the Crimea, the Gustav rail gun was to be used for the second time in fighting over this city. This city’s defenders were resupplied by the Road of Life, where vehicles would travel across a frozen lake east of this besieged city. Army Group North and their Finnish allies retreated after 900 days of fighting in, for ten points, what Soviet city that was besieged from 1941 to 1944?",
        "answer": [
          "Leningrad",
          "St. Petersburg"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This frozen lake east of Leningrad, the largest lake entirely within Europe, was used as the “Road of Life” during the siege of Leningrad.",
        "answer": "Lake Ladoga"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Revolutionary War Battles",
      "prompt": "Name the battle from the American Revolution where...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The “Shot Heard Round the World” was fired, just before the Battle of Concord.",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Lexington",
            "Battles of Lexington and Concord"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Someone legendarily said “don’t fire until you see the whites of their eyes,” fought on Breed’s Hill near Boston.",
          "answer": "Battle of Bunker Hill"
        },
        {
          "question": "The British lost many troops at Freeman’s Farm and surrendered after fighting at Bemis Heights.",
          "answer": "Battle of Saratoga"
        },
        {
          "question": "Washington’s troops captured hundreds of Hessians after crossing the Delaware River.",
          "answer": "Battle of Trenton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hugh Mercer was killed and Cornwallis was forced to abandon southern New Jersey, fought a week after the capture of the Hessians.",
          "answer": "Battle of Princeton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Molly Pitcher’s legendary heroics and Charles Lee’s infamous retreat took place.",
          "answer": "Battle of Monmouth"
        },
        {
          "question": "Johann deKalb was killed and Horatio Gates was humiliated in South Carolina.",
          "answer": "Battle of Camden"
        },
        {
          "question": "Benedict Arnold led a fleet in a successful retreat to Fort Ticonderoga, named for an island in Lake Champlain.",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Valcour Island",
            "Battle of Valcour Bay"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Battle of Actium",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Egyptian queen whose ships’ hasty retreat signaled a turn in the battle.",
          "answer": "Cleopatra VII Philopator"
        },
        {
          "question": "Losing general at Actium, the Roman lover of that Egyptian queen.",
          "answer": "Marc Antony or Marcus Antonius"
        },
        {
          "question": "Winning general who took the title “Princeps” after the battle.",
          "answer": [
            "Octavian",
            "Gaius Octavius Thurinus",
            "Caesar Augustus",
            "Augustus Caesar"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Epic poem by Virgil whose protagonist’s shield features a depiction of the battle.",
          "answer": "Aeneid"
        },
        {
          "question": "City that names the 34 BC “donations” in which Roman and Parthian land was divided up, a key cause of the war.",
          "answer": "Donations of Alexandria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Son of the Egyptian queen who was executed two weeks after his mother’s death.",
          "answer": "Caesarion or Ptolemy Caesar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gulf in the Ionian Sea at whose opening the battle was fought.",
          "answer": "Ambracian Gulf"
        },
        {
          "question": "Admiral who commanded the victorious fleet at Actium, after which he built the first Pantheon.",
          "answer": "Marcus Vipsanius Agrippa"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Mayans",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Technology whose “Long Count” type supposedly predicted the end of the world in 2012.",
          "answer": "calendar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prominent Mexican peninsula on which the Mayan civilization was centered.",
          "answer": "Yucatan Peninsula"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mayan city where the Temple of Kukulcan, a massive step-pyramid, is found.",
          "answer": "Chichen Itza"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious action carried out at a sinkhole called the Sacred Cenote to honor the rain god Chaac.",
          "answer": "human and/or child sacrifice"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mythological text of the K’iche people that describes the Hero Twins and was preserved by a Dominican friar.",
          "answer": "Popul Vuh"
        },
        {
          "question": "7th century Mayan ruler of Palenque who had the longest-known reign of any American ruler.",
          "answer": [
            "Pacal the Great",
            "Pacal I",
            "II",
            "8 Ahau",
            "Sun Shield"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mayan city in Guatemala’s Peten region, a rival of Calakmul and home of the Lost World complex.",
          "answer": [
            "Tikal",
            "Yax Mutal"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Conquistador who helped conquer Mayan settlements before helping Cortes conquer the Aztecs and governing Guatemala.",
          "answer": "Pedro de Alvarado"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Ermolao Barbaro praised a book by this man but noted that it contained over five thousand pieces of scientifically inaccurate information. Upon seeing a phenomenon that looked “like an umbrella pine,” this man journeyed from Misenum to (20 pts)",
        "rescue Rectina and Pomponianus. Although this man remarked that “fortune favors the brave,” his corpse was (10 pts)",
        "excavated from pumice at Stabiae. Letters to Tactius from this man’s nephew detail his death during the eruption of Mount Vesuvius. For ten points, name this Roman scientist, the author of Natural History."
      ],
      "answer": "Pliny the Elder"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The losing vice presidential candidate in this election year was an Oregon senator who had introduced a bill for the creation of the Grand Coulee Dam, Charles McNary. Both members of the winning ticket in this year had been interested in the philosophy of a mystic named Nicholas (20 pts)",
        "Roerich. The winning Vice Presidential candidate in this election year had earlier served as Secretary of Agriculture under the incumbent and succeeded John Nance Garner. (10 pts)",
        "Wendell Wilkie lost this election, which broke the tradition of two-term presidencies. For ten points, name this election year in which FDR won, just after the start of World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "US presidential election of 1940"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These people expanded into the Volga region under the leadership of Kotrag, a leader of the “Black” variant of these people. These people defeated their greatest foe at the Gates of Trajan after a successful defense of their capital, (20 pts)",
        "Sredets. Ninety nine out of every hundred of these people were blinded after their defeat at the Battle of Kleidion, a sight that caused King Samuel to die of shock. The (10 pts)",
        "Byzantine emperor Basil II became known as the “slayer” of, for ten points, what nomadic ethnic group who later formed a country with capital Sofia?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Bulgars",
        "Bulgarians"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Gladman and his Orchestral Jazzonions are slated to perform at one event in this play, in which one title character describes Tolstoy and Lincoln as “social reformers.” One of this play’s title characters chastises another for (20 pts)",
        "beating his girlfriend and ballroom dancing partner. This play’s first title character demands that (10 pts)",
        "Sam stop calling him “Hally” in favor of the title form of address. For ten points, name this play, set in the early years of Apartheid, by Athol Fugard."
      ],
      "answer": "Master Harold... and the Boys"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Richard Fletcher took orders from this man to build the massive Lines of Torres Vedras. This man, who led the reserves at the Battle of Seringapatam in 1799, was opposed by Anthony Pohlmann, who commanded forces for the (20 pts)",
        "Maratha ruler Raghuji Bhonsle II, at the Battle of Assaye. During the Peninsular War, this general defeated French forces at the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Salamanca, and this man joined Gebhard von Blucher in a key victory in Belgium that led to an emperor being exiled to St. Helena. For ten points, name this British general who won the 1815 Battle of Waterloo over Napoleon."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Arthur Wellesley, first Duke of Wellington",
        "either",
        "both underlined names"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One man with this surname negotiated with France to obtain a loan that allowed for the creation of the Bank of North America. That man with this surname headed the “Secret Committee of Trade” during the Second Continental Congress and is sometimes known as the (20 pts)",
        "“Financier of the Revolution.” In addition to Robert, another man with this surname wrote the phrases (10 pts)",
        "“ensure domestic Tranquility” and “form a more perfect Union” at the Constitutional Convention. For ten points, give this surname shared by Robert and the author of the Preamble, Gouverneur [“governor”]."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Morris",
        "Robert Morris",
        "Gouverneur Morris"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This oration asks its listeners to “keep pace with the progress of the world” after having “resolved to pave the way for a grand peace.” A copy of this oration was kept in a “bank vault” under the palace, preventing the leaders of the 15 August (20 pts)",
        "coup from finding it before it was smuggled out in a laundry basket. This speech concedes that, despite attempts for “self-preservation,” a joint (10 pts)",
        "declaration from China, the United States, and the USSR was accepted, and the speaker and his country must “[endure] the unendurable.” For ten points, name this speech delivered by Emperor Hirohito, announcing Japan’s surrender in World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "Jewel Voice Broadcast"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this state, William Dixon responded to the death of John Anderson by killing over 150 members of the Wintu during the Bridge Gulch Massacre. This was the southernmost of two states where a chief named Captain Jack took up positions along (20 pts)",
        "Tule Lake during the 1870’s Modoc War. At the same time as the Civil War, a group of this state’s namesake volunteers fought in this state’s (10 pts)",
        "Owens Valley Indian War. For ten points, name this state where the Pomo were killed in the 1850 Bloody Island Massacre after refusing to be forced labor during its gold rush."
      ],
      "answer": "California"
    }
  ]
}